<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 n="1" type="Book" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p>
<milestone unit="chapter" n="1" /><milestone unit="section" n="1" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Darius and Parysatis had two sons born to them, of whom the elder was Artaxerxes and the younger <persName>Cyrus</persName>.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">In regard to the persons mentioned and the events sketched in sections1-4, see Introduction, pp. 231 sqq.</note> Now when Darius lay sick and suspected that the end of his life was near, he wished to have both his sons with him.
<milestone unit="section" n="2" />The elder, as it chanced, was with him already; but <persName>Cyrus</persName> he summoned from the province over which he had made him satrap, and he had also appointed him commander of all the forces that muster in the plain of Castolus.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Castolus was the mustering place for all the Persian forces of western <placeName key="tgn,7002294" authname="tgn,7002294">Asia Minor</placeName>. See Introd. p. 232.</note> <persName>Cyrus</persName> accordingly went up<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See Introd. p. vii, note 1.</note> to his father, taking with him Tissaphernes as a friend and accompanied by three hundred Greek hoplites,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. heavy-armed infantrymen, the regular “troops of the line” in Greek warfare. In this instance, of course, they are serving <persName>Cyrus</persName> as a bodyguard.</note> under the command of Xenias of <placeName key="tgn,7017080" authname="tgn,7017080">Parrhasia</placeName>.
<milestone unit="section" n="3" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />When Darius had died and Artaxerxes had become established as king, Tissaphernes falsely accused <persName>Cyrus</persName> to his brother of plotting against him. And Artaxerxes, believing the accusation, arrested <persName>Cyrus</persName>, with the intention of putting him to death; his mother, however, made intercession for him, and sent him back again to his province.
<milestone unit="section" n="4" />Now when <persName>Cyrus</persName> had thus returned, after his danger and disgrace, he set about planning that he might never again be in the power of his brother, but, if possible, might be king in his stead. He had, in the first place, the support of Parysatis, his mother, for she loved him better than the son who was king, Artaxerxes.
<milestone unit="section" n="5" />Again, when any of the King's court came to visit him, he treated them all in such a way that when he sent them back they were more devoted to him than to the King. He also took care that the barbarians<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">“Barbarians” is a convenient, but not an accurate, translation for <foreign lang="greek">βάρβαροι,</foreign> which was simply the name the Greeks gave, without implying reproach, to all peoples who were not Greeks. In general, then, it meant “foreigners”; in most cases in the <title>Anabasis</title> (as here) it could be translated “Persians.”</note> of his own province should be capable soldiers and should feel kindly toward him.
<milestone unit="section" n="6" />Lastly, as regards his Greek force, he proceeded to collect it with the utmost secrecy, so that he might take the King as completely unprepared as possible.<milestone unit="para" ed="P" />It was in the following way, then, that he gathered this force: In the first place, he sent orders to the commanders of all the garrisons he had in the cities to enlist as many Peloponnesian soldiers of the best sort as they severally could, on the plea that Tissaphernes had designs upon their cities. For, in fact, the Ionian cities had originally belonged to Tissaphernes, by gift of the King,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See Introd. p. viii.</note> but at that time all of them except <placeName key="perseus,Miletus" authname="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName> had revolted and gone over to <persName>Cyrus</persName>.
<milestone unit="section" n="7" />The people of <placeName key="perseus,Miletus" authname="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName> also were planning to do the very same thing, namely, to go over to <persName>Cyrus</persName>, but Tissaphernes, finding out about it in time, put some of them to death and banished others. <persName>Cyrus</persName> thereupon took the exiles under his protection, collected an army, and laid siege to <placeName key="perseus,Miletus" authname="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName> both by land and by sea, and endeavoured to restore the exiles to their city; and this, again, made him another pretext for gathering an army.
<milestone unit="section" n="8" />Meanwhile he sent to the King and urged, on the ground that he was his brother, that these Ionian cities should be given to him instead of remaining under the rule of Tissaphernes, and his mother co-operated with him in this. The result was that the King failed to perceive the plot against himself, but believed that <persName>Cyrus</persName> was spending money on his troops because he was at war with Tissaphernes. Consequently he was not at all displeased at their being at war, the less so because <persName>Cyrus</persName> regularly remitted to the King the tribute which came in from the cities he chanced to have that belonged to Tissaphernes.
    <milestone unit="section" n="9" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Still another army was being collected for him in the <placeName key="tgn,1012789" authname="tgn,1012789">Chersonese</placeName> which is opposite <placeName key="perseus,Abydos,Mysia" authname="perseus,Abydos,Mysia">Abydus</placeName>, in the following manner: Clearchus<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">For the reason for his banishment see <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 2.6.2" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 2.6.2-4</bibl>.</note> was a Lacedaemonian exile; <persName>Cyrus</persName>, making his acquaintance, came to admire him, and gave him ten thousand darics.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The daric was a Persian gold coin, equivalent in weight of gold to  1 2s. 2 1/2d. or $5.40, but in purchasing power to a much larger sum.</note> And Clearchus, taking the gold, collected an army by means of this money, and using the <placeName key="tgn,1012789" authname="tgn,1012789">Chersonese</placeName> as a base of operations, proceeded to make war upon the Thracians who dwell beyond the <placeName key="tgn,7002638" authname="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName>, thereby aiding the Greeks.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. the Greeks on the European side of the Hellespont, who suffered from the incursions of their Thracian neighbours.</note> Consequently, the Hellespontine cities of their own free will sent Clearchus contributions of money for the support of his troops. So it was that this army also was being secretly maintained for <persName>Cyrus</persName>.
<milestone unit="section" n="10" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Again, Aristippus the Thessalian chanced to be a friend of <persName>Cyrus</persName>, and since he was hard pressed by his political opponents at home, he came to <persName>Cyrus</persName> and asked him for three months' pay for two thousand mercenaries, urging that in this way he should get the better of his opponents. And <persName>Cyrus</persName> gave him six months' pay for four thousand, and requested him not to come to terms with his opponents until he had consulted with him. Thus the army in <placeName key="tgn,7001399" authname="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName>, again, was being secretly maintained for him.
<milestone unit="section" n="11" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Furthermore, <persName>Cyrus</persName> directed Proxenus the Boeotian, who was a friend of his, to come to him with as many men as he could get, saying that he wished to undertake a campaign against the Pisidians, because, as he said, they were causing trouble to his province. He also directed Sophaenetus the Stymphalian and Socrates the Achaean, who were likewise friends of his, to come with as many men as they could get, saying that he intended to make war upon Tissaphernes with the aid of the Milesian exiles; and they proceeded to carry out his directions.
<milestone unit="chapter" n="2" /><milestone unit="section" n="1" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />When he thought the time had come to begin his upward<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See Introd. p. vii, note 1.</note> march, the pretext he offered was that he wished to drive the Pisidians out of his land entirely, and it was avowedly against them that he set about collecting both his barbarian and his Greek troops. At that time he also sent word to Clearchus to come to him with the entire army which he had, and to Aristippus to effect a reconciliation with his adversaries at home and send him the army which he had; and he sent word to Xenias the Arcadian, who commanded for him the mercenary force in the cities,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.1.6" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.1.6</bibl>.</note> to come with his troops, leaving behind only so many as were necessary to garrison the citadels.
<milestone unit="section" n="2" />He likewise summoned the troops which were besieging <placeName key="perseus,Miletus" authname="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName>, and urged the Milesian exiles to take the field with him, promising them that, if he should successfully accomplish the object for which he was taking the field, he would not stop until he had restored them to their homes. And they gladly obeyed—for they trusted him—and presented themselves, under arms, at <placeName key="perseus,Sardis" authname="perseus,Sardis">Sardis</placeName>.
<milestone unit="section" n="3" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Xenias, then, arrived at <placeName key="perseus,Sardis" authname="perseus,Sardis">Sardis</placeName> with the troops from the cities, who were hoplites to the number of four thousand; Proxenus was there with hoplites to the number of fifteen hundred, and five hundred light-armed troops; Sophaenetus the Stymphalian with a thousand hoplites; Socrates the Achaean with about five hundred hoplites; and Pasion the Megarian arrived with three hundred hoplites and three hundred peltasts.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Peltasts differed from ordinary light-armed troops (cp. <foreign lang="greek">γυμνῆτας</foreign> above) only in the fact that they carried a small, light shield, the <foreign lang="greek">πέλπη</foreign>—whence their name.</note> The last-named, and Socrates also, belonged to the force that had been engaged in besieging <placeName key="perseus,Miletus" authname="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName>. All these came to <persName>Cyrus</persName> at <placeName key="perseus,Sardis" authname="perseus,Sardis">Sardis</placeName>.
<milestone unit="section" n="4" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Meanwhile Tissaphernes had taken note of these proceedings and come to the conclusion that <persName>Cyrus</persName>' preparations were too extensive to be against the Pisidians; he accordingly made his way to the King as quickly as he could, with about five hundred horsemen.
<milestone unit="section" n="5" />And when the King heard from Tissaphernes about <persName>Cyrus</persName>' array, he set about making counter-preparations.<milestone unit="para" ed="P" /><persName>Cyrus</persName> was now setting forth from <placeName key="perseus,Sardis" authname="perseus,Sardis">Sardis</placeName> with the troops I have mentioned; and he marched through <placeName key="tgn,7016631" authname="tgn,7016631">Lydia</placeName> three stages,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><foreign lang="greek">σταθμός</foreign> = lit. a stopping-place, hence a day's journey.</note> a distance of twenty-two parasangs,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A Persian measure of distance, equivalent to 30 Greek stadia, or about 3.3 English miles.</note> to the <placeName key="tgn,1121561" authname="tgn,1121561">Maeander</placeName> river. The width of this river was two plethra,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The plethrum = about 97 English feet.</note> and there was a bridge over it made of seven boats.
<milestone unit="section" n="6" />After crossing the Maeander he marched through <placeName key="tgn,7002613" authname="tgn,7002613">Phrygia</placeName> one stage, a distance of eight parasangs, to <placeName key="tgn,6001508" authname="tgn,6001508">Colossae</placeName>, an inhabited<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Many of the cities of <placeName key="tgn,1000004" authname="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> were then, as now, deserted.</note> city, prosperous and large. There he remained seven days; and Menon<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Who had been sent by Aristippus (see 1 above).</note> the Thessalian arrived, with a thousand hoplites and five hundred peltasts, consisting of Dolopians, Aenianians, and Olynthians.
<milestone unit="section" n="7" />Thence he marched three stages, twenty parasangs, to Celaenae, an inhabited city of <placeName key="tgn,7002613" authname="tgn,7002613">Phrygia</placeName>, large and prosperous. There <persName>Cyrus</persName> had a palace and a large park full of wild animals, which he used to hunt on horseback whenever he wished to give himself and his horses exercise. Through the middle of this park flows the Maeander river; its sources are beneath the palace, and it flows through the city of Celaenae also.
<milestone unit="section" n="8" />There is likewise a palace of the Great King<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A title often given by the Greeks to the king of <placeName key="tgn,7000231" authname="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>.</note> in Celaenae, strongly fortified and situated at the foot of the Acropolis over the sources of the Marsyas river; the Marsyas also flows through the city, and empties into the <placeName key="tgn,1121561" authname="tgn,1121561">Maeander</placeName>, and its width is twenty-five feet. It was here, according to the story, that Apollo flayed Marsyas,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Marsyas, a Phrygian satyr, was so proud of his skill with the flute that he presumed to challenge Apollo, god of music and master of the lyre. The myth appears to be a record of the supersession of the flute by the lyre in Greek favour.</note> after having defeated him in a contest of musical skill; he hung up his skin in the cave from which the sources issue, and it is for this reason that the river is called Marsyas.
    <milestone unit="section" n="9" />It was here also, report has it, that Xerxes, when he was on his retreat from <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> after losing the famous battle,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">viz. of <placeName key="perseus,Salamis, Cyprus" authname="perseus,Salamis, Cyprus">Salamis</placeName>, in <date value="-480" authname="-480">480</date> B.C.</note> built the palace just mentioned and likewise the citadel of Celaenae. Here <persName>Cyrus</persName> remained thirty days; and Clearchus, the Lacedaemonian exile, arrived, with a thousand hoplites, eight hundred Thracian peltasts, and two hundred Cretan bowmen. At the same time came also Sosis the Syracusan with three hundred hoplites and Agias the Arcadian with a thousand hoplites. And here <persName>Cyrus</persName> held a review and made an enumeration of the Greeks in the park, and they amounted all told to eleven thousand hoplites and about two thousand peltasts.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Here used in the general sense, i.e. to include all kinds of light-armed troops; cp. note on 3 above. Xenophon here uses round numbers. The exact totals, according to the figures previously given, are 10,600 hoplites and 2,300 light-armed troops.</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="10" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Thence he marched two stages, ten parasangs, to Peltae, an inhabited city. There he remained three days, during which time Xenias the Arcadian celebrated the Lycaean<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">In honour of Lycaean Zeus, i.e. Zeus of Mt. Lycaeus, in <placeName key="tgn,7002735" authname="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>.</note> festival with sacrifice and held games; the prizes were golden strigils, and <persName>Cyrus</persName> himself was one of those who watched the games. Thence he marched two stages, twelve parasangs, to the inhabited city of Ceramon-agora,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Or Tilemarket.</note> the last Phrygian city as one goes toward <placeName key="tgn,7016748" authname="tgn,7016748">Mysia</placeName>.
<milestone unit="section" n="11" />Thence he marched three stages, thirty parasangs, to Caystru-pedion,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Or Ca sterfield.</note> an inhabited city. There he remained five days. At this time he was owing the soldiers more than three months' pay, and they went again and again to his headquarters and demanded what was due them. He all the while expressed hopes, and was manifestly troubled; for it was not <persName>Cyrus</persName>' way to withhold payment when he had money.
<milestone unit="section" n="12" />At this juncture arrived Epyaxa, the wife of Syennesis, the king<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">“King” in name, but in fact a dependent of the king of <placeName key="tgn,7000231" authname="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>. Syennesis was seeking, as the narrative indicates, to keep on good terms with both <persName>Cyrus</persName> and Artaxerxes, secretly aiding the former, while still making a show of resistance (see 21 below) to his march.</note> of the Cilicians, coming to visit <persName>Cyrus</persName>, and the story was that she gave him a large sum of money; at any rate, <persName>Cyrus</persName> paid the troops at that time four months' wages. The Cilician queen was attended by a body-guard of Cilicians and Aspendians; and people said that <persName>Cyrus</persName> had intimate relations with the queen.
<milestone unit="section" n="13" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Thence he marched two stages, ten parasangs, to the inhabited city of Thymbrium. There, alongside the road, was the so-called spring of Midas, the king of the Phrygians, at which Midas, according to the story, caught the satyr by mixing wine with the water of the spring.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">This story is less familiar than its sequel, viz. that for his kindly treatment of the satyr (Silenus) Midas was granted by Dionysus the fulfilment of any request he might make; he requested that all he touched should turn to gold, and so died of hunger.</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="14" />Thence he marched two stages, ten parasangs, to Tyriaeum, an inhabited city. There he remained three days. And the Cilician queen, as the report ran, asked <persName>Cyrus</persName> to exhibit his army to her; such an exhibition was what he desired to make, and accordingly he held a review of the Greeks and the barbarians on the plain.
<milestone unit="section" n="15" />He ordered the Greeks to form their lines and take their positions just as they were accustomed to do for battle, each general marshalling his own men. So they formed the line four deep, Menon and his troops occupying the right wing, Clearchus and his troops the left, and the other generals the centre.
<milestone unit="section" n="16" /><persName>Cyrus</persName> inspected the barbarians first, and they marched past with their cavalry formed in troops and their infantry in companies; then he inspected the Greeks, driving past them in a chariot, the Cilician queen in a carriage. And the Greeks all had helmets of bronze, crimson tunics, and greaves, and carried their shields uncovered.
<milestone unit="section" n="17" />When he had driven past them all, he halted his chariot in front of the centre of the phalanx, and sending his interpreter Pigres to the generals of the Greeks, gave orders that the troops should advance arms and the phalanx move forward in a body. The generals transmitted these orders to the soldiers, and when the trumpet sounded, they advanced arms and charged. And then, as they went on faster and faster, at length with a shout the troops broke into a run of their own accord, in the direction of the camp.
<milestone unit="section" n="18" />As for the barbarians, they were terribly frightened; the Cilician queen took to flight in her carriage, and the people in the market<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Greek troops were not supplied with rations in the modern way, but bought their provisions from day to day from sutlers who accompanied the army. The commander's duty ended with “providing a market” (<foreign lang="greek">ἀγορὰν παρέχειν</foreign>).</note> left their wares behind and took to their heels; while the Greeks with a roar of laughter came up to their camp. Now the Cilician queen was filled with admiration at beholding the brilliant appearance and the order of the Greek army; and <persName>Cyrus</persName> was delighted to see the terror with which the Greeks inspired the barbarians.
<milestone unit="section" n="19" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Thence he marched three stages, twenty parasangs, to <placeName key="tgn,7002539" authname="tgn,7002539">Iconium</placeName>, the last city of <placeName key="tgn,7002613" authname="tgn,7002613">Phrygia</placeName>. There he remained three days. Thence he marched through <placeName key="tgn,1003785" authname="tgn,1003785">Lycaonia</placeName> five stages, thirty parasangs. This country he gave over to the Greeks to plunder, on the ground that it was hostile territory.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">In leaving Phrygia <persName>Cyrus</persName> was passing beyond the limits of his own satrapy. Introd. p. viii.</note>
    <milestone unit="section" n="20" />From there <persName>Cyrus</persName> sent the Cilician queen back to <placeName key="tgn,7002470" authname="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName> by the shortest route, and he sent some of Menon's troops to escort her, Menon himself commanding them. With the rest of the army <persName>Cyrus</persName> marched through <placeName key="tgn,6003016" authname="tgn,6003016">Cappadocia</placeName> four stages, twenty-five parasangs, to <placeName key="perseus,Tyana" authname="perseus,Tyana">Dana</placeName>, an inhabited city, large and prosperous. There they remained three days; and during that time <persName>Cyrus</persName> put to death a Persian named Megaphernes, who was a wearer of the royal purple,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A title of honour at the Persian court.</note> and another dignitary among his subordinates, on the charge that they were plotting against him.
<milestone unit="section" n="21" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />From there they made ready to try to enter <placeName key="tgn,7002470" authname="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName>. Now the entrance was by a wagon-road, exceedingly steep and impracticable for an army to pass if there was anybody to oppose it; and in fact, as report ran, Syennesis was upon the heights, guarding the entrance; therefore <persName>Cyrus</persName> remained for a day in the plain. On the following day, however, a messenger came with word that Syennesis had abandoned the heights, because he had learned that Menon's army was already in <placeName key="tgn,7002470" authname="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName>, on his own side of the mountains, and because, further, he was getting reports that triremes belonging to the Lacedaemonians<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><persName>Cyrus</persName> had asked the Lacedaemonians “to show themselves as good friends to him as he had been to them in their war against <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>” (<bibl n="Xen. Hell. 2.1.1" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Hell. 2.1.1</bibl>). The aid they now rendered (see also <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.4.2" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.4.2-3</bibl>) was in response to that request.</note> and to <persName>Cyrus</persName> himself were sailing around from <placeName key="tgn,6002765" authname="tgn,6002765">Ionia</placeName> to <placeName key="tgn,7002470" authname="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName> under the command of Tamos.
<milestone unit="section" n="22" />At any rate<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. whether or not the reasons just given were the true ones.</note> <persName>Cyrus</persName> climbed the mountains without meeting any opposition, and saw the camp where the Cilicians had been keeping guard. Thence he descended to a large and beautiful plain, well-watered and full of trees of all sorts and vines; it produces an abundance of sesame, millet, panic, wheat, and barley, and it is surrounded on every side, from sea to sea, by a lofty and formidable range of mountains.
<milestone unit="section" n="23" />After descending he marched through this plain four stages, twenty-five parasangs, to <placeName key="perseus,Tarsus" authname="perseus,Tarsus">Tarsus</placeName>,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The birth-place of the apostle Paul.</note> a large and prosperous city of <placeName key="tgn,7002470" authname="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName>, where the palace of Syennesis, the king of the Cilicians, was situated; and through the middle of the city flows a river named the Cydnus, two plethra in width.
<milestone unit="section" n="24" />The inhabitants of this city had abandoned it and fled, with Syennesis, to a stronghold upon the mountains—all of them, at least, except the tavern-keepers; and there remained also those who dwelt on the sea-coast, in <placeName key="perseus,Soli" authname="perseus,Soli">Soli</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7002542" authname="tgn,7002542">Issus</placeName>.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Famous as the scene of one of the most important victories of Alexander the Great (<date value="-333" authname="-333">333</date> B.C.).</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="25" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Now Epyaxa, the wife of Syennesis, had reached <placeName key="perseus,Tarsus" authname="perseus,Tarsus">Tarsus</placeName> five days ahead of <persName>Cyrus</persName>, but in the course of her passage over the mountains to the plain two companies of Menon's army<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">cp. 20, above.</note> had been lost. Some said that they had been cut to pieces by the Cilicians while engaged in a bit of plundering; another story was that they had been left behind, and, unable to find the rest of the army or the roads, had thus wandered about and perished; at any rate, they numbered a hundred hoplites.
<milestone unit="section" n="26" />And when the rest of Menon's troops reached <placeName key="perseus,Tarsus" authname="perseus,Tarsus">Tarsus</placeName>, in their anger over the loss of their comrades they plundered thoroughly, not only the city, but also the palace that was in it. As for <persName>Cyrus</persName>, after he had marched into the city he more than once summoned Syennesis to his presence; but Syennesis said that he had never yet put himself in the hands of anyone who was more powerful than he was, and he would not now put himself in the hands of <persName>Cyrus</persName> until his wife had won him over and he had received pledges.
<milestone unit="section" n="27" />When the two men finally met one another, Syennesis gave <persName>Cyrus</persName> a large sum of money for his army, while <persName>Cyrus</persName> gave him gifts which are regarded at court<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. such gifts as could be bestowed only by the Persian king. <persName>Cyrus</persName> is already assuming royal prerogatives.</note> as tokens of honour—a horse with a gold-mounted bridle, a gold necklace and bracelets, a gold dagger and a Persian robe—promising him, further, that his land should not be plundered any more and that they might take back the slaves that had been seized in case they should chance upon them anywhere.
<milestone unit="chapter" n="3" /><milestone unit="section" n="1" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" /><persName>Cyrus</persName> and his army remained here at <placeName key="perseus,Tarsus" authname="perseus,Tarsus">Tarsus</placeName> twenty days, for the soldiers refused to go any farther; for they suspected by this time that they were going against the King, and they said they had not been hired for that. Clearchus was the first to try to force his men to go on, but they pelted him and his pack-animals with stones as often as they began to go forward.
<milestone unit="section" n="2" />At that time Clearchus narrowly escaped being stoned to death; but afterwards, when he realized that he could not accomplish anything by force, he called a meeting of his own troops. And first he stood and wept for a long time, while his men watched him in wonder and were silent; then he spoke as follows:
<milestone unit="section" n="3" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />“Fellow-soldiers, do not wonder that I am distressed at the present situation. For <persName>Cyrus</persName> became my friend and not only honoured me, an exile from my fatherland, in various ways, but gave me ten thousand darics. And I, receiving this money, did not lay it up for my own personal use or squander it in pleasure, but I proceeded to expend it on you.
    <milestone unit="section" n="4" />First I went to war with the Thracians, and for the sake of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> I inflicted punishment upon them with your aid, driving them out of the <placeName key="tgn,1012789" authname="tgn,1012789">Chersonese</placeName> when they wanted to deprive the Greeks who dwelt there of their land. Then when <persName>Cyrus</persName>' summons came, I took you with me and set out, in order that, if he had need of me, I might give him aid in return for the benefits I had received from him.
<milestone unit="section" n="5" />But you now do not wish to continue the march with me; so it seems that I must either desert you and continue to enjoy <persName>Cyrus</persName>' friendship, or prove false to him and remain with you. Whether I shall be doing what is right, I know not, but at any rate I shall choose you and with you shall suffer whatever I must. And never shall any man say that I, after leading Greeks into the land of the barbarians, betrayed the Greeks and chose the friendship of the barbarians;
<milestone unit="section" n="6" />nay, since you do not care to obey me, I shall follow with you and suffer whatever I must. For I consider that you are to me both fatherland and friends and allies; with you I think I shall be honoured wherever I may be, bereft of you I do not think I shall be able either to aid a friend or to ward off a foe. Be sure, therefore, that wherever you go, I shall go also.”
<milestone unit="section" n="7" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Such were his words. And the soldiers—not only his own men, but the rest also—when they heard that he said he would not go on to the King's capital, commended him; and more than two thousand of the troops under Xenias and Pasion took their arms and their baggage train and encamped with Clearchus.
<milestone unit="section" n="8" />But <persName>Cyrus</persName>, perplexed and distressed by this situation, sent repeatedly for Clearchus. Clearchus refused to go to him, but without the knowledge of the soldiers he sent a messenger and told him not to be discouraged, because, he said, this matter would be settled in the right way. He directed <persName>Cyrus</persName>, however, to keep on sending for him, though he himself, he said, would refuse to go.
<milestone unit="section" n="9" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />After this Clearchus gathered together his own soldiers, those who had come over to him, and any others who wanted to be present, and spoke as follows: “Fellow-soldiers, it is clear that the relation of <persName>Cyrus</persName> to us is precisely the same as ours to him; that is, we are no longer his soldiers, since we decline to follow him, and likewise he is no longer our paymaster.
<milestone unit="section" n="10" />I know, however, that he considers himself wronged by us. Therefore, although he keeps sending for me, I decline to go, chiefly, it is true, from a feeling of shame, because I am conscious that I have proved utterly false to him, but, besides that, from fear that he may seize me and inflict punishment upon me for the wrongs he thinks he has suffered at my hands.
<milestone unit="section" n="11" />In my opinion, therefore, it is no time for us to be sleeping or unconcerned about ourselves; we should rather be considering what course we ought to follow under the present circumstances. And so long as we remain here we must consider, I think, how we can remain most safely; or, again, if we count it best to depart at once, how we are to depart most safely and how we shall secure provisions—for without provisions neither general nor private is of any use.
<milestone unit="section" n="12" />And remember that while this <persName>Cyrus</persName> is a valuable friend when he is your friend, he is a most dangerous foe when he is your enemy; furthermore, he has an armament—infantry and cavalry and fleet—which we all alike see and know about; for I take it that our camp is not very far away from him. It is time, then, to propose whatever plan any one of you deems best.” With these words he ceased speaking.
<milestone unit="section" n="13" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Thereupon various speakers arose, some of their own accord to express the opinions they held, but others at the instigation of Clearchus to make clear the difficulty of either remaining or departing without the consent of <persName>Cyrus</persName>.
<milestone unit="section" n="14" />One man in particular, pretending to be in a hurry to proceed back to <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> with all speed, proposed that they should choose other generals as quickly as possible, in case Clearchus did not wish to lead them back; secondly, that they should buy provisions—the market was in the barbarian army!—and pack up their baggage; then, to go to <persName>Cyrus</persName> and ask for vessels to sail away in; and if he would not give them vessels, to ask him for a guide to lead them homeward through a country that was friendly; and if he would not give them a guide, either, to form in line of battle with all speed and likewise to send a force to occupy the mountain heights in advance, in order that neither <persName>Cyrus</persName> nor the Cilicians should forestall them—“and we have in our possession,” he said, “many of these Cilicians and much of their property that we have seized as plunder.” Such were the words of this speaker.
<milestone unit="section" n="15" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />After him Clearchus said merely this: “Let no one among you speak of me as the man who is to hold this command, for I see many reasons why I should not do so; say rather that I shall obey to the best of my ability the man whom you choose, in order that you may know that I understand as well as any other person in the world how to be a subordinate also.”
<milestone unit="section" n="16" />After he had spoken another man arose to point out the foolishness of the speaker who had urged them to ask for vessels, just as if <persName>Cyrus</persName> were going home again, and to point out also how foolish it was to ask for a guide “from this man whose enterprise we are ruining. Indeed, if we propose to trust the guide that <persName>Cyrus</persName> gives us, what is to hinder us from directing <persName>Cyrus</persName> also to occupy the heights for us in advance?
<milestone unit="section" n="17" />For my part, I should hesitate to embark on the vessels that he might give us, for fear of his sinking us with his war-ships, and I should be afraid to follow the guide that he might give, for fear of his leading us to a place from which it will not be possible to escape; my choice would be, in going off without <persName>Cyrus</persName>' consent, to go off without his knowledge—and that is not possible.
<milestone unit="section" n="18" />Now in my own opinion the plans just proposed are nonsense; rather, I think we should send to <persName>Cyrus</persName> men of the proper sort, along with Clearchus, to ask him what use he wishes to make of us; and if his enterprise is like the sort of one in which he employed mercenaries before,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">As described in <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.1.2" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.1.2</bibl>.</note> I think that we also should follow him and not be more cowardly than those who went up with him on the former occasion;
<milestone unit="section" n="19" />if, however, his enterprise is found to be greater and more laborious and more dangerous than the former one, we ought to demand that he should either offer sufficient persuasion<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. in the form of extra pay.</note> and lead us on with him, or yield to our persuasion and let us go home in friendship; for in this way, if we should follow him, we should follow as friends and zealous supporters, and if we should go back, we should go back in safety. I propose, further, that our representatives should report back to us whatever reply he may make, and that we after hearing it should deliberate about the matter.”
<milestone unit="section" n="20" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />This plan was adopted, and they chose representatives and sent them with Clearchus; and they proceeded to put to <persName>Cyrus</persName> the questions resolved upon by the army. He replied that he had heard that Abrocomas, a foe of his, was at the Euphrates river, twelve stages distant. It was against him, therefore, he said, that he desired to march. And if he were there, he wished to inflict due punishment upon him; “but if he has fled,” he continued, “we will deliberate about the matter then and there.”
<milestone unit="section" n="21" />Upon hearing this reply the deputies reported it to the soldiers, and they, while suspecting that <persName>Cyrus</persName> was leading them against the King, nevertheless thought it best to follow him. They asked, however, for more pay, and <persName>Cyrus</persName> promised to give them all half as much again as they had been receiving before, namely, a daric and a half a month to each man instead of a daric; but as regards the suspicion that he was leading them against the King, no one heard it expressed even then—at any rate, not openly.
<milestone unit="chapter" n="4" /><milestone unit="section" n="1" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Thence he marched two stages, ten parasangs, to the Psarus river, the width of which was three plethra. From there he marched one stage, five parasangs, to the Pyramus river, the width of which was a stadium.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The stadium = 582 1/2 English feet.</note> From there he marched two stages, fifteen parasangs, to <placeName key="tgn,7002542" authname="tgn,7002542">Issus</placeName>, the last city in <placeName key="tgn,7002470" authname="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName>, a place situated on the sea, and large and prosperous.
    <milestone unit="section" n="2" />There they remained three days; and the ships from <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName><note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.2.21" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.2.21</bibl>.</note> arrived to meet <persName>Cyrus</persName>, thirty-five in number, with Pythagoras the Lacedaemonian as admiral in command of them. They had been guided from <placeName key="perseus,Ephesos" authname="perseus,Ephesos">Ephesus</placeName> to <placeName key="tgn,7002542" authname="tgn,7002542">Issus</placeName> by Tamos the Egyptian, who was at the head of another fleet of twenty-five ships belonging to <persName>Cyrus</persName>—these latter being the ships with which Tamos had besieged <placeName key="perseus,Miletus" authname="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName>, at the time when it was friendly to Tissaphernes,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.1.7" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.1.7</bibl>.</note> and had supported <persName>Cyrus</persName> in his war upon Tissaphernes.
<milestone unit="section" n="3" />Cheirisophus the Lacedaemonian also arrived with this fleet, coming in response to <persName>Cyrus</persName>' summons,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See note on <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.2.21" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.2.21</bibl>. These seven hundred hoplites under Cheirisophus had been sent by the Lacedaemonian authorities to aid <persName>Cyrus</persName>, and were the only troops in his army which stood in any official connection with any Greek state.</note> together with seven hundred hoplites, over whom he continued to hold command in the army of <persName>Cyrus</persName>. And the ships lay at anchor alongside <persName>Cyrus</persName>' tent. It was at <placeName key="tgn,7002542" authname="tgn,7002542">Issus</placeName> also that the Greek mercenaries who had been in the service of Abrocomas—four hundred hoplites—joined <persName>Cyrus</persName>, after deserting Abrocomas, and so bore a share in his expedition against the King.
<milestone unit="section" n="4" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Thence he marched one stage, five parasangs, to the Gates between <placeName key="tgn,7002470" authname="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,1000140" authname="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>. These Gates consisted of two walls; the one on the hither, or Cilician, side was held by Syennesis and a garrison of Cilicians, while the one on the farther, the Syrian, side was reported to be guarded by a garrison of the King's troops. And in the space between these walls flows a river named the Carsus, a plethrum in width. The entire distance from one wall to the other was three stadia; and it was not possible to effect a passage by force, for the pass was narrow, the walls reached down to the sea, and above the pass were precipitous rocks, while, besides, there were towers upon both the walls.
<milestone unit="section" n="5" />It was because of this pass that <persName>Cyrus</persName> had sent for the fleet, in order that he might disembark hoplites between and beyond the walls and thus overpower the enemy if they should be keeping guard at the Syrian Gates—and that was precisely what <persName>Cyrus</persName> supposed Abrocomas would do, for he had a large army. Abrocomas, however, did not do so, but as soon as he heard that <persName>Cyrus</persName> was in <placeName key="tgn,7002470" authname="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName>, he turned about in his journey from <placeName key="tgn,6004687" authname="tgn,6004687">Phoenicia</placeName><note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Of which Abrocomas was satrap.</note> and marched off to join the King, with an army, so the report ran, of three hundred thousand men.
<milestone unit="section" n="6" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Thence <persName>Cyrus</persName> marched one stage, five parasangs, to Myriandus, a city on the sea coast, inhabited by Phoenicians; it was a trading place, and many merchant ships were lying at anchor there. There he remained seven days;
<milestone unit="section" n="7" />and Xenias the Arcadian and Pasion the Megarian embarked upon a ship, put on board their most valuable effects, and sailed away; they were moved to do this, as most people thought, by a feeling of jealous pride, because their soldiers had gone over to Clearchus<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.3.7" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.3.7</bibl>.</note> with the intention of going back to <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> again instead of proceeding against the King, and <persName>Cyrus</persName> had allowed Clearchus to keep them. After they had disappeared, a report went round that <persName>Cyrus</persName> was pursuing them with warships; and while some people prayed that they might be captured, because, as they said, they were cowards, yet others felt pity for them if they should be caught.
<milestone unit="section" n="8" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" /><persName>Cyrus</persName>, however, called the generals together and said: “Xenias and Pasion have deserted us. But let them, nevertheless, know full well that they have not escaped from me—either by stealth, for I know in what direction they have gone, or by speed, for I have men-of-war with which I can overtake their craft. But for my part, I swear by the gods that I shall not pursue them, nor shall anyone say about me that I use a man so long as he is with me and then, when he wants to leave me, seize him and maltreat him and despoil him of his possessions. Nay, let them go, with the knowledge that their behaviour toward us is worse than ours toward them. To be sure, I have their wives and children under guard in <placeName key="perseus,Tralleis" authname="perseus,Tralleis">Tralles</placeName>,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A city in <placeName key="tgn,7002358" authname="tgn,7002358">Caria</placeName>.</note> but I shall not deprive them of these, either, for they shall receive them back because of their former excellence in my service.”
<milestone unit="section" n="9" />Such were his words; as for the Greeks, even those who had been somewhat despondent in regard to the upward march, when they heard of the magnanimity of <persName>Cyrus</persName> they continued on their way with greater satisfaction and eagerness.<milestone unit="para" ed="P" />After this <persName>Cyrus</persName> marched four stages, twenty parasangs, to the Chalus river, which is a plethrum in width and full of large, tame fish; these fish the Syrians regarded as gods, and they would not allow anyone to harm them, or the doves, either.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">According to the legend, the Syrian goddess Derceto had been transformed into a fish, and her daughter, Semiramis, into a dove.</note> And the villages in which the troops encamped belonged to Parysatis, for they had been given her for girdle-money.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">cp. the English “pin-money.”</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="10" />From there <persName>Cyrus</persName> marched five stages, thirty parasangs, to the sources of the Dardas river, the width of which is a plethrum. There was the palace of Belesys, the late ruler of <placeName key="tgn,1000140" authname="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>, and a very large and beautiful park containing all the products of the seasons. But <persName>Cyrus</persName> cut down the park and burned the palace.
<milestone unit="section" n="11" />Thence he marched three stages, fifteen parasangs, to the Euphrates river, the width of which was four stadia; and on the river was situated a large and prosperous city named <placeName key="tgn,6005911" authname="tgn,6005911">Thapsacus</placeName>. There he remained five days. And <persName>Cyrus</persName> summoned the generals of the Greeks and told them that the march was to be to <placeName key="tgn,7002626" authname="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, against the Great King; he directed them, accordingly, to explain this to the soldiers and try to persuade them to follow.
<milestone unit="section" n="12" />So the generals called an assembly and made this announcement; and the soldiers were angry with the generals, and said that they had known about this for a long time, but had been keeping it from the troops; furthermore, they refused to go on unless they were given money,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The troops are not now asking for additional pay, as at <placeName key="perseus,Tarsus" authname="perseus,Tarsus">Tarsus</placeName> (<bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.3.21" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.3.21</bibl>), but for a special donation. See below.</note> as were the men who made the journey with <persName>Cyrus</persName> before,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.1.2" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.1.2</bibl>.</note> when he went to visit his father; they had received the donation, even though they marched, not to battle, but merely because <persName>Cyrus</persName>' father summoned him.
<milestone unit="section" n="13" />All these things the generals reported back to <persName>Cyrus</persName>, and he promised that he would give every man five minas<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The Attic mina was equivalent (but see note on <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.1.9" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.1.9</bibl>) to about  3 1 5s. or $18.00; <persName>Cyrus</persName> probably means here the Persian mina, which was worth about one-fourth more than the Attic.</note> in silver when they reached <placeName key="tgn,7002626" authname="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName> and their pay in full until he brought the Greeks back to <placeName key="tgn,6002765" authname="tgn,6002765">Ionia</placeName> again.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Mercenaries were usually expected to make their own way home after a campaign had ended and did not receive pay for the time consumed by the homeward journey.</note> By these promises the greater part of the Greek army was persuaded.<milestone unit="para" ed="P" />But as for Menon, before it was clear what the rest of the soldiers would do, that is, whether they would follow <persName>Cyrus</persName> or not, he gathered together his own troops apart from the others and spoke as follows:
<milestone unit="section" n="14" />“Soldiers, if you will obey me, you will, without either danger or toil, be honoured by <persName>Cyrus</persName> above and beyond the rest of the troops. What, then, do I direct you to do? At this moment <persName>Cyrus</persName> is begging the Greeks to follow him against the King; my own plan, then, is that you should cross the Euphrates river before it is clear what answer the rest of the Greeks will make to <persName>Cyrus</persName>.
<milestone unit="section" n="15" />For if they vote to follow him, it is you who will get the credit for that decision because you began the crossing, and <persName>Cyrus</persName> will not only feel grateful to you, regarding you as the most zealous in his cause, but he will return the favour—and he knows how to do that if any man does; on the other hand, if the rest vote not to follow him, we shall all go back together, but you, as the only ones who were obedient, are the men he will employ, not only for garrison duty,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. easy service.</note> but for captaincies; and whatever else you may desire, I know that you, as friends of <persName>Cyrus</persName>, will secure from him.”
<milestone unit="section" n="16" />Upon hearing these words the soldiers were persuaded, and made the crossing before the rest gave their answer. When <persName>Cyrus</persName> learned that they had crossed, he was delighted and sent Glus to the troops with this message: “Soldiers, to-day I commend you; but I shall see to it that you also shall have cause to commend me, else count me no longer <persName>Cyrus</persName>.”
<milestone unit="section" n="17" />So Menon's troops cherished high hopes and prayed that he might be successful, while to Menon himself <persName>Cyrus</persName> was said to have sent magnificent gifts besides. After so doing <persName>Cyrus</persName> proceeded to cross the river, and the rest of the army followed him, to the last man. And in the crossing no one was wetted above the breast by the water.
<milestone unit="section" n="18" />The people of <placeName key="tgn,6005911" authname="tgn,6005911">Thapsacus</placeName> said that this river had never been passable on foot except at this time, but only by boats; and these Abrocomas had now burned, as he marched on ahead of <persName>Cyrus</persName>, in order to prevent him from crossing. It seemed, accordingly, that here was a divine intervention, and that the river had plainly retired before <persName>Cyrus</persName> because he was destined to be king.
<milestone unit="section" n="19" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Thence he marched through <placeName key="tgn,1000140" authname="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> nine stages, fifty parasangs, and they arrived at the Araxes river. There they found many villages full of grain and wine, and there they remained for three days and provisioned the army.
<milestone unit="chapter" n="5" /><milestone unit="section" n="1" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Thence he marched through <placeName key="tgn,1012700" authname="tgn,1012700">Arabia</placeName>, keeping the <placeName key="tgn,1123842" authname="tgn,1123842">Euphrates</placeName> on the right, five stages through desert country, thirty-five parasangs. In this region the ground was an unbroken plain, as level as the sea, and full of wormwood; and whatever else there was on the plain by way of shrub or reed, was always fragrant, like spices;
<milestone unit="section" n="2" />trees there were none, but wild animals of all sorts, vast numbers of wild asses and many ostriches, besides bustards and gazelles. These animals were sometimes chased by the horsemen. As for the asses, whenever one chased them, they would run on ahead and stop—for they ran much faster than the horses—and then, when the horses came near, they would do the same thing again, and it was impossible to catch them unless the horsemen posted themselves at intervals and hunted them in relays. The flesh of those that were captured was like venison, but more tender.
<milestone unit="section" n="3" />But no ostrich was captured by anyone, and any horseman who chased one speedily desisted; for it would distance him at once in its flight, not merely plying its feet, but hoisting its wings and using them like a sail. The bustards, on the other hand, can be caught if one is quick in starting them up, for they fly only a short distance, like partridges, and soon tire; and their flesh was delicious.
<milestone unit="section" n="4" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Marching on through this region they arrived at the Mascas river, which is a plethrum in width. There, in the desert, was a large city named Corsote, completely surrounded by the Mascas.
<milestone unit="section" n="5" />There they remained three days and provisioned the army. Thence <persName>Cyrus</persName> marched thirteen stages through desert country, ninety parasangs, keeping the Euphrates river on the right, and arrived at Pylae. In the course of these stages many of the baggage animals died of hunger, for there was no fodder and, in fact, no growing thing of any kind, but the land was absolutely bare; and the people who dwelt here made a living by quarrying mill-stones along the river banks, then fashioning them and taking them to <placeName key="tgn,7002626" authname="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, where they sold them and bought grain in exchange.
<milestone unit="section" n="6" />As for the troops, their supply of grain gave out, and it was not possible to buy any except in the Lydian<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The Lydians were notorious as hucksters.</note> market attached to the barbarian army of <persName>Cyrus</persName>,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.2.18" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.2.18</bibl> and the note thereon, and <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.3.14" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.3.14</bibl>.</note> at the price of four sigli for a capith of wheat flour or barley meal. The siglus is worth seven and one-half Attic obols, and the capith had the capacity of two Attic choenices.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The obol = about 1 1/2d. or 3 cents. The choenix = about 1 quart. The prices stated were, roughly, about fifty times normal prices at <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note> The soldiers therefore managed to subsist by eating meat.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The Greeks of Xenophon's time ate comparatively little meat under any circumstances, but in the Arabian desert a diet of meat constituted a real hardship.</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="7" />And <persName>Cyrus</persName> sometimes made these stages through the desert very long, whenever he wanted to reach water or fresh fodder.<milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Once in particular, when they came upon a narrow, muddy place which was hard for the wagons to get through, <persName>Cyrus</persName> halted with his train of nobles and dignitaries and ordered Glus and Pigres to take some of the barbarian troops and help to pull the wagons out.
<milestone unit="section" n="8" />But it seemed to him that they took their time with the work; accordingly, as if in anger, he directed the Persian nobles who accompanied him to take a hand in hurrying on the wagons. And then one might have beheld a sample of good discipline: they each threw off their purple cloaks where they chanced to be standing, and rushed, as a man would run to win a victory, down a most exceedingly steep hill, wearing their costly tunics and coloured trousers, some of them, indeed, with necklaces around their necks and bracelets on their arms; and leaping at once, with all this finery, into the mud, they lifted the wagons high and dry and brought them out more quickly than one would have thought possible.
<milestone unit="section" n="9" />In general, it was clear that <persName>Cyrus</persName> was in haste throughout the whole journey and was making no delays, except where he halted to procure provisions or for some other necessary purpose; his thought was that the faster he went, the more unprepared the King would be to fight with him, while, on the other hand, the slower he went, the greater would be the army that was gathering for the King. Furthermore, one who observed closely could see at a glance that while the King's empire was strong in its extent of territory and number of inhabitants, it was weak by reason of the greatness of the distances and the scattered condition of its forces, in case one should be swift in making his attack upon it.
<milestone unit="section" n="10" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Across the Euphrates river in the course of these desert marches was a large and prosperous city named Charmande, and here the soldiers made purchases of provisions, crossing the river on rafts in the following way: they took skins which they had for tent covers, filled them with hay, and then brought the edges together and sewed them up, so that the water could not touch the hay; on these they would cross and get provisions—wine made from the date of the palm tree and bread made of millet, for this grain was very abundant in the country.
<milestone unit="section" n="11" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />There one of Menon's soldiers and one of Clearchus' men had some dispute, and Clearchus, deciding that Menon's man was in the wrong, gave him a flogging. The man then went to his own army and told about it, and when his comrades heard of the matter, they took it hard and were exceedingly angry with Clearchus.
<milestone unit="section" n="12" />On the same day Clearchus, after going to the place where they crossed the river and there inspecting the market, was riding back to his own tent through Menon's army, having only a few men with him; and <persName>Cyrus</persName> had not yet arrived, but was still on the march toward the place; and one of Menon's soldiers who was splitting wood threw his axe at Clearchus when he saw him riding through the camp. Now this man missed him, but another threw a stone at him, and still another, and then, after an outcry had been raised, many.
<milestone unit="section" n="13" />Clearchus escaped to his own army and at once called his troops to arms; he ordered his hoplites to remain where they were, resting their shields against their knees,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. in readiness to support him in case of need.</note> while he himself with the Thracians<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.2.9" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.2.9</bibl>.</note> and the horsemen, of which he had in his army more than forty, most of them Thracians, advanced upon Menon's troops; the result was that these and Menon himself were thoroughly frightened and ran to their arms, though there were some who stood stock-still, nonplussed by the situation.
<milestone unit="section" n="14" />But Proxenus—for he chanced to be now coming up, later than the others, with a battalion of hoplites following him—straightway led his troops into the space between the two parties, halted them under arms, and began to beg Clearchus not to proceed with his attack. Clearchus, however, was angry, because, when he had barely escaped being stoned to death, Proxenus was talking lightly of his grievance, and he ordered him to remove himself from between them.
<milestone unit="section" n="15" />At this moment <persName>Cyrus</persName> also came up and learned about the situation, and he immediately took his spears in his hands and, attended by such of his counsellors as were present, came riding into the intervening space and spoke as follows:
<milestone unit="section" n="16" />“Clearchus, and Proxenus, and all you other Greeks who are here, you know not what you are doing. For as certainly as you come to fighting with one another, you may be sure that on this very day I shall be instantly cut to pieces and yourselves not long after me; for once let ill fortune overtake us, and all these barbarians whom you see will be more hostile to us than are those who stand with the King.”
<milestone unit="section" n="17" />On hearing these words Clearchus came to his senses, and both parties ceased from their quarrel and returned to their quarters.
<milestone unit="chapter" n="6" /><milestone unit="section" n="1" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />As they went on from there, they kept seeing tracks of horses and horses' dung. To all appearances it was the trail of about two thousand horses, and the horsemen as they proceeded were burning up fodder and everything else that was of any use. At this time Orontas, a Persian, who was related to the King by birth and was reckoned among the best of the Persians in matters of war, devised a plot against <persName>Cyrus</persName>—in fact, he had made war upon him before this, but had become his friend again.
<milestone unit="section" n="2" />He now said to <persName>Cyrus</persName> that if he would give him a thousand horsemen, he would either ambush and kill these horsemen who were burning ahead of him, or he would capture many of them alive and put a stop to their burning as they advanced; and he would see to it that they should never be able to behold <persName>Cyrus</persName>' army and get to the King with their report. When <persName>Cyrus</persName> heard this plan, it seemed to him to be an expedient one, and he directed Orontas to get a detachment from each one of the cavalry commanders.
<milestone unit="section" n="3" />Then Orontas, thinking that his horsemen were assured him, wrote a letter to the King saying that he would come to him with as many horsemen as he could get; and he urged the King to direct his own cavalry to receive him as a friend. The letter also contained reminders of his former friendship and fidelity. This letter he gave to a man whom he supposed to be faithful to him; but this man took it and gave it to <persName>Cyrus</persName>.
<milestone unit="section" n="4" />When <persName>Cyrus</persName> had read it, he had Orontas arrested, and summoned to his tent seven of the noblest Persians among his attendants, while he ordered the Greek generals to bring up hoplites and bid them station themselves under arms around his tent. And the generals obeyed the order, bringing with them about three thousand hoplites.
<milestone unit="section" n="5" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Clearchus was also invited into the tent as a counsellor, for both <persName>Cyrus</persName> and the other Persians regarded him as the man who was honoured above the rest of the Greeks. And when he came out, he reported to his friends how Orontas' trial was conducted—for it was no secret.
<milestone unit="section" n="6" />He said that <persName>Cyrus</persName> began the conference in this way: “My friends, I have invited you here in order that I may consult with you and then take such action in the case of Orontas here as is right in the sight of gods and men. This man was given me at first by my father, to be my subject; then, at the bidding, as he himself said, of my brother, this man levied war upon me, holding the citadel of <placeName key="perseus,Sardis" authname="perseus,Sardis">Sardis</placeName>, and I, by the war I waged against him, made him count it best to cease from warring upon me, and I received and gave the hand-clasp of friendship. Since that,” he said, “Orontas, have I done you any wrong?”
<milestone unit="section" n="7" />“No,” Orontas answered. <persName>Cyrus</persName> went on questioning him: “Did you not afterwards, although, as you yourself admit, you had suffered no wrong at my hands, desert me for the Mysians, and do all the harm you could to my territory?” “Yes,” said Orontas. “Did you not,” <persName>Cyrus</persName> said, “when once more you had learned the slightness of your own power, go to the altar of Artemis and say you were sorry, and did you not, after prevailing upon me to pardon you, again give me pledges and receive pledges from me?” This also Orontas admitted.
<milestone unit="section" n="8" />“What wrong, then,” said <persName>Cyrus</persName>, “have you suffered at my hands, that you now for the third time have been found plotting against me?” When Orontas replied, “None,” <persName>Cyrus</persName> asked him: “Do you admit, then, that you have proved yourself a doer of wrong toward me?” “I cannot choose but do so,” said Orontas. Thereupon <persName>Cyrus</persName> asked again: “Then could you henceforth prove yourself a foe to my brother and a faithful friend to me?” “Even if I should do so <persName>Cyrus</persName>,” he replied, “you could never after this believe it of me.”
<milestone unit="section" n="9" />Then <persName>Cyrus</persName> said to those who were present: “Such have been this man's deeds, such are now his words; and now, Clearchus, do you be the first of my counsellors to express the opinion you hold.” And Clearchus said: “My advice is to put this man out of the way as speedily as possible, so that we may no longer have to be on our guard against the fellow, but may be left free, so far as concerns him, to requite with benefits these willing servants.”
<milestone unit="section" n="10" />In this opinion Clearchus said that the others also concurred.<milestone unit="para" ed="P" />After this, he said, at the bidding of <persName>Cyrus</persName>, every man of them arose, even Orontas' kinsmen, and took him by the girdle, as a sign that he was condemned to death; and then those to whom the duty was assigned led him out. And when the men who in former days were wont to do him homage saw him, they made their obeisance even then, although they knew that he was being led forth to death.
<milestone unit="section" n="11" />Now after he had been conducted into the tent of Artapates, the most faithful of <persName>Cyrus</persName>' chamberlains, from that moment no man ever saw Orontas living or dead, nor could anyone say from actual knowledge how he was put to death,—it was all conjectures, of one sort and another; and no grave of his was ever seen.
    <milestone unit="chapter" n="7" /><milestone unit="section" n="1" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />From there <persName>Cyrus</persName> marched through <placeName key="tgn,7013255" authname="tgn,7013255">Babylonia</placeName> three stages, twelve parasangs. On the third stage he held a review of the Greeks and the barbarians on the plain at about midnight; for he thought that at the next dawn the King would come with his army to do battle; and he ordered Clearchus to act as commander of the right wing and Menon of the left, while he himself marshalled his own troops.
<milestone unit="section" n="2" />On the morning following the review, at daybreak, there came deserters from the great King and brought reports to <persName>Cyrus</persName> about his army.<milestone unit="para" ed="P" />At this time <persName>Cyrus</persName> called together the generals and captains of the Greeks, and not only took counsel with them as to how he should fight the battle, but, for his own part, exhorted and encouraged them as follows:
<milestone unit="section" n="3" />“Men of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, it is not because I have not barbarians enough that I have brought you hither to fight for me; but because I believe that you are braver and stronger than many barbarians, for this reason I took you also. Be sure, therefore, to be men worthy of the freedom you possess, upon the possession of which I congratulate you. For you may be certain that freedom is the thing I should choose in preference to all that I have and many times more.
<milestone unit="section" n="4" />And now, in order that you may know what sort of a contest it is into which you are going, I who do know will tell you. Our enemies have great numbers and they will come on with a great outcry; for the rest, however, if you can hold out against these things, I am ashamed, I assure you, to think what sorry fellows you will find the people of our country to be. But if you be men and if my undertaking turn out well, I shall make anyone among you who wishes to return home an object of envy to his friends at home upon his return, while I shall cause many of you, I imagine, to choose life with me in preference to life at home.”
<milestone unit="section" n="5" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Hereupon Gaulites, a Samian exile who was there and was in the confidence of <persName>Cyrus</persName>, said: “And yet, <persName>Cyrus</persName>, there are those who say that your promises are big now because you are in such a critical situation—for the danger is upon you—but that if any good fortune befall, you will fail to remember them; and some say that even if you should remember and have the will, you would not have the means to make good all your promises.”
<milestone unit="section" n="6" />Upon hearing these words <persName>Cyrus</persName> said: “Well, gentlemen, my father's realm extends toward the south to a region where men cannot dwell by reason of the heat, and to the north to a region where they cannot dwell by reason of the cold; and all that lies between these limits my brother's friends rule as satraps.
<milestone unit="section" n="7" />Now if we win the victory, we must put our friends in control of these provinces. I fear, therefore, not that I shall not have enough to give to each of my friends, if success attends us, but that I shall not have enough friends to give to. And as for you men of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, I shall give each one of you a wreath of gold besides.”
<milestone unit="section" n="8" />When they heard these words, the officers were far more eager themselves and carried the news away with them to the other Greeks. Then some of the others also sought <persName>Cyrus</persName>' presence, demanding to know what they should have, in case of victory; and he satisfied the expectations of every one of them before dismissing them.
<milestone unit="section" n="9" />Now all alike who conversed with him urged him not to take part in the fighting, but to station himself in their rear. Taking this opportunity Clearchus asked <persName>Cyrus</persName> a question like this: “But do you think, <persName>Cyrus</persName>, that your brother will fight with you?” “Yes, by Zeus,” said <persName>Cyrus</persName>, “if he is really a son of Darius and Parysatis and a brother of mine, I shall not win this realm without fighting for it.”
<milestone unit="section" n="10" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />At this time, when the troops were marshalled under arms,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. in the review mentioned in 1.</note> the number of the Greeks was found to be ten thousand four hundred hoplites, and two thousand five hundred peltasts,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">There is a discrepancy, as yet unexplained, between these numbers and those previously given. cp. <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.2.9" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.2.9</bibl> and note; also <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.2.25" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.2.25</bibl> and <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.4.3" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.4.3</bibl>.</note> while the number of the barbarians under <persName>Cyrus</persName> was one hundred thousand and there were about twenty scythe-bearing chariots.
<milestone unit="section" n="11" />The enemy, it was reported, numbered one million two hundred thousand<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The number is probably overstated. Ctesias, the King's Greek physician (see viii. 26), is said by Plutarch (<title>Artax.</title> 13) to have given it as 400,000.</note> and had two hundred scythe-bearing chariots; besides, there was a troop of six thousand horsemen, under the command of Artagerses, which was stationed in front of the King himself.
<milestone unit="section" n="12" />And the King's army had four commanders, each at the head of three hundred thousand men, namely, Abrocomas, Tissaphernes, Gobryas, and Arbaces. But of the forces just enumerated only nine hundred thousand, with one hundred and fifty scythe-bearing chariots, were present at the battle; for Abrocomas, marching from <placeName key="tgn,6004687" authname="tgn,6004687">Phoenicia</placeName>, arrived five days too late for the engagement.
<milestone unit="section" n="13" />Such were the reports brought to <persName>Cyrus</persName> by those who deserted from the Great King before the battle, and after the battle identical reports were made by the prisoners taken thereafter.
<milestone unit="section" n="14" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />From there <persName>Cyrus</persName> marched one stage, three parasangs, with his whole army, Greek and barbarian alike, drawn up in line of battle; for he supposed that on that day the King would come to an engagement; for about midway of this day's march there was a deep trench, five fathoms<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><foreign lang="greek">ὀργυά</foreign> = the reach of the outstretched arms (cp. <foreign lang="greek">ὀρέγω</foreign>), or, as an exact unit of measurement, 6 Greek feet = 5 ft. 10 in. English measure.</note> in width and three fathoms in depth.
<milestone unit="section" n="15" />This trench extended up through the plain for a distance of twelve parasangs, reaching to the wall of Media,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Described by Xenophon in <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 2.4.12" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 2.4.12</bibl>. It extended from the <placeName key="tgn,1123842" authname="tgn,1123842">Euphrates</placeName> north east to the <placeName key="tgn,1130850" authname="tgn,1130850">Tigris</placeName>, and was built by the Babylonians, apparently in the sixth century B.C., as a defence against the Medes. It is supposed that the southern part of the wall was now in ruins. Such a supposition serves to explain (1) the need of the King's trench, and (2) the fact that Xenophon does not describe the wall here, but only in <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 2.4.12" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 2.4.12</bibl>.</note> [Here also are the canals, which flow from the Tigris river; they are four in number, each a plethrum wide and exceedingly deep, and grain-carrying ships ply in them; they empty into the <placeName key="tgn,1123842" authname="tgn,1123842">Euphrates</placeName> and are a parsang apart, and there are bridges over them.] and alongside the <placeName key="tgn,1123842" authname="tgn,1123842">Euphrates</placeName> there was a narrow passage, not more than about twenty feet in width, between the river and the trench;
<milestone unit="section" n="16" />and the trench<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">It would seem that the rapid approach of <persName>Cyrus</persName> had prevented the King from completing the trench.</note> had been constructed by the Great King as a means of defence when he learned that <persName>Cyrus</persName> was marching against him. Accordingly <persName>Cyrus</persName> and his army went through by the passage just mentioned, and so found themselves on the inner side of the trench.
<milestone unit="section" n="17" />Now on that day the King did not offer battle, but tracks of both horses and men in retreat were to be seen in great numbers.
<milestone unit="section" n="18" />Then <persName>Cyrus</persName> summoned <placeName key="tgn,1046911" authname="tgn,1046911">Silanus</placeName>, his Ambraciot soothsayer, and gave him three thousand darics; for on the eleventh day before this, while sacrificing, he had told <persName>Cyrus</persName> that the King would not fight within ten days, and <persName>Cyrus</persName> had said: “Then he will not fight at all, if he will not fight within ten days; however, if your prediction proves true, I promise you ten talents.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Hence 10 (Attic) talents = 3,000 (Persian) darics. A talent was 60 minas, and therefore a mina was counted equivalent to 5 darics. The discrepancy between this result and the values stated previously (see notes on i. 9 and iv. 13) is explained by the fact that silver was worth much more at this time, relatively to gold, than at present.</note>” So it was this money that he then paid over, the ten days having passed.
<milestone unit="section" n="19" />But since the King did not appear at the trench and try to prevent the passage of <persName>Cyrus</persName>' army, both <persName>Cyrus</persName> and the rest concluded that he had given up the idea of fighting. Hence on the following day <persName>Cyrus</persName> proceeded more carelessly;
<milestone unit="section" n="20" />and on the third day he was making the march seated in his chariot and with only a small body of troops drawn up in line in front of him, while the greater part of the army was proceeding in disorder and many of the soldiers' arms and accoutrements were being carried in wagons and on pack-animals.
<milestone unit="chapter" n="8" /><milestone unit="section" n="1" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />It was now about full-market time<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. the middle of the forenoon.</note> and the stopping-place where <persName>Cyrus</persName> was intending to halt had been almost reached, when Pategyas, a trusty Persian of <persName>Cyrus</persName>' staff, came into sight, riding at full speed, with his horse in a sweat, and at once shouted out to everyone he met, in the barbarian tongue and in Greek, that the King was approaching with a large army, all ready for battle.
<milestone unit="section" n="2" />Then ensued great confusion; for the thought of the Greeks, and of all the rest in fact, was that he would fall upon them immediately, while they were in disorder;
<milestone unit="section" n="3" />and <persName>Cyrus</persName> leaped down from his chariot, put on his breastplate, and then, mounting his horse, took his spears in his hands and passed the word to all the others to arm themselves and get into their places, every man of them.
<milestone unit="section" n="4" />Thereupon they proceeded in great haste to take their places, Clearchus occupying the right end of the Greek wing,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. the Greek army as a whole constituted the right wing of <persName>Cyrus</persName>' entire army, his Persian troops forming the centre and the left wing. Clearchus and Menon, then, occupy the right and left wings, respectively, of the Greek contingent.</note> close to the Euphrates river, Proxenus next to him, and the others beyond Proxenus, while Menon and his army took the left end of the Greek wing.
<milestone unit="section" n="5" />As for the barbarians, Paphlagonian horsemen to the number of a thousand took station beside Clearchus on the right wing, as did the Greek peltasts, on the left was Ariaeus, <persName>Cyrus</persName>' lieutenant, with the rest of the barbarian army,
<milestone unit="section" n="6" />and in the centre <persName>Cyrus</persName> and his horsemen, about six hundred in number. These troopers were armed with breastplates and thigh-pieces and, all of them except <persName>Cyrus</persName>, with helmets—<persName>Cyrus</persName>, however, went into the battle with his head unprotected. [In fact, it is said of the Persians in general that they venture all the perils of war with their heads unprotected.]
<milestone unit="section" n="7" />And all their horses [with <persName>Cyrus</persName>] had frontlets and breast-pieces; and the men carried, besides their other weapons, Greek sabres.
<milestone unit="section" n="8" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />And now it was midday, and the enemy were not yet in sight; but when afternoon was coming on, there was seen a rising dust, which appeared at first like a white cloud, but some time later like a kind of blackness in the plain, extending over a great distance. As the enemy came nearer and nearer, there were presently flashes of bronze here and there, and spears and the hostile ranks began to come into sight.
<milestone unit="section" n="9" />There were horsemen in white cuirasses on the left wing of the enemy, under the command, it was reported, of Tissaphernes; next to them were troops with wicker shields and, farther on, hoplites with wooden shields which reached to their feet, these latter being Egyptians, people said; and then more horsemen and more bowmen. All these troops were marching in national divisions, each nation in a solid square.
<milestone unit="section" n="10" />In front of them were the so-called scythe-bearing chariots, at some distance from one another; and the scythes they carried reached out sideways from the axles and were also set under the chariot bodies, pointing towards the ground, so as to cut to pieces whatever they met; the intention, then, was that they should drive into the ranks of the Greeks and cut the troops to pieces.
<milestone unit="section" n="11" />As for the statement, however, which <persName>Cyrus</persName> made when he called the Greeks together and urged them to hold out against the shouting of the barbarians, he proved to be mistaken in this point; for they came on, not with shouting, but in the utmost silence and quietness, with equal step and slowly.
<milestone unit="section" n="12" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />At this moment <persName>Cyrus</persName> rode along the line, attended only by Pigres, his interpreter, and three or four others, and shouted to Clearchus to lead his army against the enemy's centre, for the reason that the King was stationed there; “and if,” he said, “we are victorious there, our whole task is accomplished.”
<milestone unit="section" n="13" />Clearchus, however, since he saw the compact body at the enemy's centre and heard from <persName>Cyrus</persName> that the King was beyond his left wing (for the King was so superior in numbers that, although occupying the centre of his own line, he was beyond <persName>Cyrus</persName>' left wing), was unwilling to draw the right wing away from the river, for fear that he might be turned on both flanks; and he told <persName>Cyrus</persName>, in reply, that he was taking care to make everything go well.
<milestone unit="section" n="14" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />At this critical time the King's army was advancing evenly, while the Greek force, still remaining in the same place, was forming its line from those who were still coming up. And <persName>Cyrus</persName>, riding along at some distance from his army, was taking a survey, looking in either direction, both at his enemies and his friends.
<milestone unit="section" n="15" />Then Xenophon,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The author. He always speaks of himself in the third person.</note> an Athenian, seeing him from the Greek army, approached so as to meet him and asked if he had any orders to give; and <persName>Cyrus</persName> pulled up his horse and bade Xenophon tell everybody that the sacrificial victims and omens were all favourable.
<milestone unit="section" n="16" />While saying this he heard a noise running through the ranks, and asked what the noise was. Xenophon replied that the watchword was now passing along for the second time.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. back again, from the last man to the first.</note> And <persName>Cyrus</persName> wondered who had given it out, and asked what the watchword was. Xenophon replied “Zeus Saviour and Victory.”
<milestone unit="section" n="17" />And upon hearing this <persName>Cyrus</persName> said, “Well, I accept it, and so let it be.” After he had said these words he rode back to his own position.<milestone unit="para" ed="P" />At length the opposing lines were not three or four stadia apart, and then the Greeks struck up the paean and began to advance against the enemy.
<milestone unit="section" n="18" />And when, as they proceeded, a part of the phalanx billowed out, those who were thus left behind began to run; at the same moment they all set up the sort of war-cry which they raise to Enyalius,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. Ares.</note> and all alike began running. It is also reported that some of them clashed their shields against their spears, thereby frightening the enemy's horses.
<milestone unit="section" n="19" />And before an arrow reached them, the barbarians broke and fled. Thereupon the Greeks pursued with all their might, but shouted meanwhile to one another not to run at a headlong pace, but to keep their ranks in the pursuit.
<milestone unit="section" n="20" />As for the enemy's chariots, some of them plunged through the lines of their own troops, others, however, through the Greek lines, but without charioteers. And whenever the Greeks saw them coming, they would open a gap for their passage; one fellow, to be sure, was caught, like a befuddled man on a race-course, yet it was said that even he was not hurt in the least, nor, for that matter, did any other single man among the Greeks get any hurt whatever in this battle, save that some one on the left wing was reported to have been hit by an arrow.
<milestone unit="section" n="21" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />When <persName>Cyrus</persName> saw that the Greeks were victorious over the division opposite them and were in pursuit, although he was pleased and was already being saluted with homage as King by his attendants, he nevertheless was not induced to join the pursuit, but, keeping in close formation the six hundred horsemen of his troop, he was watching to see what the King would do. For he knew that the King held the centre of the Persian army;
<milestone unit="section" n="22" />in fact, all the generals of the barbarians hold their own centre when they are in command, for they think that this is the safest position, namely, with their forces on either side of them, and also that if they want to pass along an order, the army will get it in half the time;
<milestone unit="section" n="23" />so in this instance the King held the centre of the army under his command, but still he found himself beyond the left wing of <persName>Cyrus</persName>. Since, then, there was no one in his front to give battle to him or to the troops drawn up before him, he proceeded to wheel round his line with the intention of encircling the enemy.
<milestone unit="section" n="24" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Thereupon <persName>Cyrus</persName>, seized with fear lest he might get in the rear of the Greek troops and cut them to pieces, charged to meet him; and attacking with his six hundred, he was victorious over the forces stationed in front of the King and put to flight the six thousand,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.7.11" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.7.11</bibl>.</note> slaying with his own hand, it is said, their commander Artagerses.
<milestone unit="section" n="25" />But when they turned to flight, <persName>Cyrus</persName>' six hundred, setting out in pursuit, became scattered also, and only a very few were left about him, chiefly his so-called table companions.
<milestone unit="section" n="26" />While attended by these only, he caught sight of the King and the compact body around him; and on the instant he lost control of himself and, with the cry “I see the man,” rushed upon him and struck him in the breast and wounded him through his breastplate—as Ctesias<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See note on <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.7.11" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.7.11</bibl>.</note> the physician says, adding also that he himself healed the wound.
<milestone unit="section" n="27" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />While <persName>Cyrus</persName> was delivering his stroke, however, some one hit him a hard blow under the eye with a javelin; and then followed a struggle between the King and <persName>Cyrus</persName> and the attendants who supported each of them. The number that fell on the King's side is stated by Ctesias, who was with him; on the other side, <persName>Cyrus</persName> himself was killed and eight of the noblest of his attendants lay dead upon him.
<milestone unit="section" n="28" />Of Artapates, the one among <persName>Cyrus</persName>' chamberlains who was his most faithful follower, it is told that when he saw <persName>Cyrus</persName> fallen, he leaped down from his horse and threw his arms about him.
<milestone unit="section" n="29" />And one report is that the King ordered someone to slay him upon the body of <persName>Cyrus</persName>, while others say that he drew his dagger and slew himself with his own hand; for he had a dagger of gold, and he also wore a necklace and bracelets and all the other ornaments that the noblest Persians wear; for he had been honoured by <persName>Cyrus</persName> because of his affection and fidelity.
<milestone unit="chapter" n="9" /><milestone unit="section" n="1" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />In this way, then, <persName>Cyrus</persName> came to his end, a man who was the most kingly and the most worthy to rule of all the Persians who have been born since <persName>Cyrus</persName> the Elder, as all agree who are reputed to have known <persName>Cyrus</persName> intimately.
<milestone unit="section" n="2" />For firstly, while he was still a boy and was being educated with his brother and the other boys, he was regarded as the best of them all in all respects.
<milestone unit="section" n="3" />For all the sons of the noblest Persians are educated at the King's court. There one may learn discretion and self-control in full measure, and nothing that is base can be either heard or seen.
<milestone unit="section" n="4" />The boys have before their eyes the spectacle of men honoured by the King and of others dishonoured; they likewise hear of them; and so from earliest boyhood they are learning how to rule and how to submit to rule.
<milestone unit="section" n="5" />Here, then, <persName>Cyrus</persName> was reputed to be, in the first place, the most modest of his fellows, and even more obedient to his elders than were his inferiors in rank; secondly, the most devoted to horses and the most skilful in managing horses; he was also adjudged the most eager to learn, and the most diligent in practising, military accomplishments, alike the use of the bow and of the javelin.
<milestone unit="section" n="6" />Then, when he was of suitable age, he was the fondest of hunting and, more than that, the fondest of incurring danger in his pursuit of wild animals. On one occasion, when a bear charged upon him, he did not take to flight, but grappled with her and was dragged from his horse; he received some injuries, the scars of which he retained, but in the end he killed the bear; and, furthermore, the man who was the first to come to his assistance he made an object of envy to many.
<milestone unit="section" n="7" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Again, when he was sent down<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See Introd., p. vii, note 1; also <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.1.2" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.1.2</bibl>.</note> by his father to be satrap of <placeName key="tgn,7016631" authname="tgn,7016631">Lydia</placeName>, Greater Phrygia, and <placeName key="tgn,6003016" authname="tgn,6003016">Cappadocia</placeName> and was also appointed commander of all the troops whose duty it is to muster in the plain of Castolus, he showed, in the first place, that he counted it of the utmost importance, when he concluded a treaty or compact with anyone or made anyone any promise, under no circumstances to prove false to his word.
<milestone unit="section" n="8" />It was for this reason, then, that the cities trusted him and put themselves under his protection,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.1.6" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.1.6</bibl> fin.</note> and that individuals also trusted him; and if anyone had been an enemy, when <persName>Cyrus</persName> made a treaty with him he trusted that he would suffer no harm in violation of that treaty.
<milestone unit="section" n="9" />Consequently, when he came to hostilities with Tissaphernes, all the cities of their own accord chose <persName>Cyrus</persName> rather than Tissaphernes, with the exception of <placeName key="perseus,Miletus" authname="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName>;<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.1.7" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.1.7</bibl> and <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.2.2" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.2.2</bibl>.</note> and the reason why the Milesians feared him was, that he would not prove false to the exiles from their city.
<milestone unit="section" n="10" />For he showed repeatedly, by deed as well as by word, that he would never abandon them when once he had come to be their friend, not even if they should become still fewer in number and should meet with still worse misfortune.
<milestone unit="section" n="11" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />It was manifest also that whenever a man conferred any benefit upon <persName>Cyrus</persName> or did him any harm, he always strove to outdo him; in fact, some people used to report it as a prayer of his that he might live long enough to outdo both those who benefited and those who injured him, returning like for like.
<milestone unit="section" n="12" />Hence it was that he had a greater following than any other one man of our time of friends who eagerly desired to entrust to him both treasure and cities and their very bodies.
<milestone unit="section" n="13" />Yet, on the other hand, none could say that he permitted malefactors and wicked men to laugh at him; on the contrary, he was merciless to the last degree in punishing them, and one might often see along the travelled roads people who had lost feet or hands or eyes; thus in <persName>Cyrus</persName>' province it became possible for either Greek or barbarian, provided he were guilty of no wrongdoing, to travel fearlessly wherever he wished, carrying with him whatever it was to his interest to have.
<milestone unit="section" n="14" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />But it was the brave in war, as all agree, whom he honoured especially. For example, he was once at war with the Pisidians and Mysians and commanded in person an expedition into their territories; and whomsoever in his army he found willing to meet dangers, these men he would not only appoint as rulers of the territory he was subduing, but would honour thereafter with other gifts also.
<milestone unit="section" n="15" />Thus the brave were seen to be most prosperous, while cowards were deemed fit to be their slaves. Consequently <persName>Cyrus</persName> had men in great abundance who were willing to meet danger wherever they thought that he would observe them.
<milestone unit="section" n="16" />As for uprightness, if a man showed that he desired to distinguish himself in that quality, <persName>Cyrus</persName> considered it all important to enable such an one to live in greater opulence than those who were greedy of unjust gain.
<milestone unit="section" n="17" />Hence he not only had many and various functions performed for him with fidelity, but, in particular, he secured the services of an army worthy of the name. For generals and captains who came overseas to serve him for the sake of money judged that loyal obedience to <persName>Cyrus</persName> was worth more to them than their mere monthly pay.
<milestone unit="section" n="18" />Again, so surely as a man performed with credit any service that he assigned him, <persName>Cyrus</persName> never let his zeal go unrewarded. In consequence, he was said to have gained the very best supporters for every undertaking.
<milestone unit="section" n="19" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Furthermore, whenever he saw that a man was a skilful and just administrator, not only organizing well the country over which he ruled, but producing revenues, he would never deprive such a man of territory, but would always give him more besides. The result was that they toiled with pleasure and accumulated with confidence, and, more than that, no one would conceal from <persName>Cyrus</persName> the store which he had acquired; for it was clear that he did not envy those who were frankly and openly rich, but strove to make use of the possessions of such as tried to conceal their wealth.
<milestone unit="section" n="20" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />As to friends, all agree that he showed himself pre-eminent in his attentions to all the friends that he made and found devoted to him and adjudged to be competent co-workers in whatever he might be wishing to accomplish.
<milestone unit="section" n="21" />For, just as the precise object for which he thought he needed friends himself was that he might have co-workers, so he tried on his own part to be a most vigorous co-worker with his friends to secure that which he found each one of them desired.
<milestone unit="section" n="22" />Again, he received more gifts, I presume, than any other one man, and for many reasons; and surely he of all men distributed gifts most generously among his friends, with an eye to the tastes of each one and to whatever particular need he noted in each case.
<milestone unit="section" n="23" />As for all the gifts which people sent him to wear upon his person, whether intended for war or merely for show, it is reported that he said of them that his own person could not be adorned with all these things, but that in his opinion friends nobly adorned were a man's greatest ornament.
<milestone unit="section" n="24" />To be sure, the fact that he outdid his friends in the greatness of the benefits he conferred is nothing surprising, for the manifest reason that he had greater means than they; but that he surpassed them in solicitude and in eagerness to do favours, this in my opinion is more admirable.
<milestone unit="section" n="25" />For example, when <persName>Cyrus</persName> got some particularly good wine, he would often send the half-emptied jar to a friend with the message: “<persName>Cyrus</persName> says that he has not chanced upon better wine than this for a long time; so he sends it to you, and asks you to drink it up today in company with the friends you love best.”
<milestone unit="section" n="26" />So he would often send halves of geese and of loaves and so forth, instructing the bearer to add the message: “<persName>Cyrus</persName> enjoyed this, and therefore wants you also to take a taste of it.”
<milestone unit="section" n="27" />And wherever fodder was exceedingly scarce and he was able to get it for his own use because of the large number of his servants and because of his good planning, he would distribute this fodder among his friends and tell them to give it to the horses that carried their own bodies, that they might not be hungry while carrying his friends.
<milestone unit="section" n="28" />And whenever he was on the march and was likely to be seen by very many people, he would call his friends to him and engage them in earnest conversation, in order to show whom he honoured. Hence, as I at least conclude from what comes to my ears, no man, Greek or barbarian, has ever been loved by a greater number of people.
<milestone unit="section" n="29" />Here is a fact to confirm that conclusion: although <persName>Cyrus</persName> was a slave,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A term habitually applied by the Greeks to the subjects of an absolute monarch, especially those of the Persian king.</note> no one deserted him to join the King, save that Orontas attempted to do so (and he, mark you, speedily found out that the man he imagined was faithful to him, was more devoted to <persName>Cyrus</persName> than to him); on the other hand, many went over from the King to <persName>Cyrus</persName> after the two had become enemies (these being, moreover, the men who were most highly regarded by the King), because they thought that if they were deserving, they would gain a worthier reward with <persName>Cyrus</persName> than with the King.
<milestone unit="section" n="30" />Furthermore, what happened to <persName>Cyrus</persName> at the end of his life is a strong indication that he was a true man himself and that he knew how to judge those who were faithful, devoted, and constant.
<milestone unit="section" n="31" />When he died, namely, all his bodyguard of friends and table companions died fighting in his defence, with the exception of Ariaeus; he, it chanced, was stationed on the left wing at the head of the cavalry, and when he learned that <persName>Cyrus</persName> had fallen, he took to flight with the whole army that he commanded.
<milestone unit="chapter" n="10" /><milestone unit="section" n="1" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Then the head of <persName>Cyrus</persName> and his right hand were cut off. But the King, pursuing Ariaeus, burst into the camp of <persName>Cyrus</persName>; and Ariaeus and his men no longer stood their ground, but fled through their own camp to the stopping-place from which they had set out that morning, a distance, it was said, of four parasangs.
<milestone unit="section" n="2" />So the King and his troops proceeded to secure plunder of various sorts in abundance, while in particular he captured the Phocaean woman, <persName>Cyrus</persName>' concubine, who, by all accounts, was clever and beautiful.
<milestone unit="section" n="3" />The Milesian woman, however, the younger one, after being seized by the King's men made her escape, lightly clad, to some Greeks who had chanced to be standing guard amid the baggage train and, forming themselves in line against the enemy, had killed many of the plunderers, although some of their own number had been killed also; nevertheless, they did not take to flight, but they saved this woman and, furthermore, whatever else came within their lines, whether persons or property, they saved all alike.
<milestone unit="section" n="4" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />At this time the King and the Greeks were distant from one another about thirty stadia, the Greeks pursuing the troops in their front, in the belief that they were victorious over all the enemy, the King and his followers plundering, in the belief that they were all victorious already.
<milestone unit="section" n="5" />When, however, the Greeks learned that the King and his forces were in their baggage train, and the King, on the other hand, heard from Tissaphernes that the Greeks were victorious over the division opposite them and had gone on ahead in pursuit, then the King proceeded to gather his troops together and form them in line of battle, and Clearchus called Proxenus (for he was nearest him in the line) and took counsel with him as to whether they should send a detachment or go in full force to the camp, for the purpose of lending aid.
<milestone unit="section" n="6" />Meanwhile the Greeks saw the King advancing again, as it seemed, from their rear, and they accordingly countermarched and made ready to meet his attack in case he should advance in that direction<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The Greeks had advanced straight forward from their position on the right wing and the King straight forward from his centre (which was beyond the left wing of <persName>Cyrus</persName>' entire, i.e. Greek and barbarian, army); hence the two had passed by one another at a considerable distance. The question now was, whether the King on his return march would move obliquely, so as to meet the Greeks, or would follow the same route by which he advanced, thus keeping clear of them again.</note>; the King, however, did not do so, but returned by the same route he had followed before, when he passed outside of <persName>Cyrus</persName>' left wing, and in his return picked up not only those who had deserted to the Greeks during the battle, but also Tissaphernes and his troops.
<milestone unit="section" n="7" />For Tissaphernes had not taken to flight in the first encounter, but had charged along the river through the Greek peltasts<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.8.4" default="NO" valid="yes">Xen. Anab. 1.8.4-5</bibl>.</note>; he did not kill anyone in his passage, but the Greeks, after opening a gap for his men, proceeded to deal blows and throw javelins upon them as they went through. The commander of the Greek peltasts was Episthenes of <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis" authname="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>, and it was said that he proved himself a sagacious man.
<milestone unit="section" n="8" />At any rate, after Tissaphernes had thus come off with the worst of it, he did not wheel round again, but went on to the camp of the Greeks and there fell in with the King; so it was that, after forming their lines once more, they were proceeding together.
<milestone unit="section" n="9" /><milestone unit="para" ed="P" />When they were over against the left wing of the Greeks,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">At this point the fronts of the two armies—which were facing in opposite directions, and, further, each in the direction opposite to that which it took in the first encounter—were in approximately the same straight line. It should be noted that Xenophon means by “the left wing” of the Greeks that which had been the left wing in the original formation, but had now become the right.</note> the latter conceived the fear that they might advance against that wing and, by outflanking them on both sides, cut them to pieces; they thought it best, therefore, to draw the wing back and get the river in their rear.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The Greek line was now, as in the beginning, at right angles to the <placeName key="tgn,1123842" authname="tgn,1123842">Euphrates</placeName>. The movement here described would (if executed) have made it parallel to the river, the latter serving as a defence in the rear.</note>
<milestone unit="section" n="10" />But while they were taking counsel about this matter, the King had already changed his line of battle to the same form as theirs and brought it into position opposite them, just as when he had met them for battle the first time.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Xenophon seems to mean that the King now moved to the right until his flank (like that of the Greeks—see the preceding notes) rested upon the <placeName key="tgn,1123842" authname="tgn,1123842">Euphrates</placeName>. The two armies, therefore, were again squarely facing one another, though with positions relatively reversed (see note 2 above).</note> And when the Greeks saw that the enemy were near them and in battle-order, they again struck up the paean and advanced to the attack much more eagerly than before;
<milestone unit="section" n="11" />and the barbarians once again failed to await the attack, but took to flight when at a greater distance from the Greeks than they were the first time.
<milestone unit="section" n="12" />The Greeks pursued as far as a certain village, and there they halted; for above the village was a hill, upon which the King and his followers rallied; and they were not now foot-soldiers, but the hill was covered with horsemen, so that the Greeks could not perceive what was going on. They did see, they said, the royal standard, a kind of golden eagle on a shield, raised aloft upon a pole.
<milestone unit="section" n="13" />But when at this point also the Greeks resumed their forward movement, the horsemen at once proceeded to leave the hill; they did not keep together, however, as they went, but scattered in different directions; so the hill became gradually cleared of the horsemen, till at last they were all gone.
<milestone unit="section" n="14" />Clearchus, accordingly, did not lead the army up the hill, but halted at its foot and sent Lycius the Syracusan and another man to the summit, directing them to observe what was beyond the hill and report back to him.
<milestone unit="section" n="15" />And Lycius, after riding up and looking, brought back word that the enemy were in headlong flight.
<milestone unit="section" n="16" />At about this time the sun set.<milestone unit="para" ed="P" />Then the Greeks halted, grounded arms, and proceeded to rest themselves. At the same time they wondered that <persName>Cyrus</persName> was nowhere to be seen and that no one else had come to them from him; for they did not know that he was dead, but conjectured that he had either gone off in pursuit or pushed on to occupy some point.
<milestone unit="section" n="17" />So they took counsel for themselves as to whether they should remain where they were and bring the baggage train thither, or return to their camp. The decision was to return, and they reached their tents about supper-time.
<milestone unit="section" n="18" />Such was the conclusion of this day. They found most of their property pillaged, in particular whatever there was to eat or drink, and as for the wagons loaded with flour and wine which <persName>Cyrus</persName> had provided in order that, if ever serious need should overtake the army, he might have supplies to distribute among the Greeks (and there were four hundred of these wagons, it was said), these also the King and his men had now pillaged.
<milestone unit="section" n="19" />The result was that most of the Greeks had no dinner; and they had had no breakfast, either, for the King had appeared before the time when the army was to halt for breakfast. Thus it was, then that they got through this night.</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>